<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on mxinden</title>
    <link>https://max-inden.de/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on mxinden</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://max-inden.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi there, I am Max, a software developer interested in distributed systems.
You can best reach me via e-mail: mail@max-inden.de.
GPG Fingerprint: 4110045EE7A432D67AFAC8C85403C5464810BC26</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resume</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/resume/</guid>
      <description>Experience Software Engineer at Parity | July 2019 - Present
Maintaining Rust peer-to-peer networking library libp2p and its usage within the Blockchain framework Substrate. Involved in the networking logic of the main byzantine fault tolerant finality gadget finality-grandpa. Filling role of hiring manager for team building automated testing infrastructure. Shepherding (Prometheus) monitoring across the company.
Freelance Network Engineer at SpaceNet AG | Jun 2019
Work on multiplexed fiber-optic setup and server migration.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Misc</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/misc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/misc/</guid>
      <description>Projects &amp;amp; Achievements   2019-01-16 to 2019-08-02 - Maintainer of Kubernetes kube-state-metrics.
  2019-01-15 - Joining Kubernetes organisation.
  2019-01-11 - Kubernetes kube-state-metrics performance optimization dividing CPU usage by a factor of 6 and memory and response time by a factor of 3 through introducing an intelligent Prometheus metric cache in the code hot path and optimizing memory allocations during response generation.
  2018-09-04 - Design, specification and implementation of a new API (v2) for Prometheus Alertmanager, generated via OpenAPI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Know your latencies</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-06-19-latencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-06-19-latencies/</guid>
      <description>I find it helpful to know the orders of magnitude by which certain computer operations differ. Certainly it is not worth the effort to pay attention to every digit or learn these by heart, especially since they differ (slightly) across systems, but having a basic understanding of what a tiny fraction of time a CPU cycle occupies compared to sending a TCP packet is incredibly helpful whenever reasoning about systems performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>26th DistSys Reading Group - Cache coherence</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-05-18-26th-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-05-18-26th-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>We have long been planning to cover the caching mechanisms in CPUs. As a shared knowledge base for the discussions in this session we chose the following two articles by Martin Thompson among other things known for his work on the LMAX Disruptor:
  CPU Cache Flushing Fallacy including a good overview over the different caches in modern Intel CPUs.
  Write Combining exemplifying the advanced mechanisms one can find in today&amp;rsquo;s CPUs and how one can make use of them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>25th DistSys Reading Group - Fair queuing</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-04-27-25th-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-04-27-25th-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>In the session today we covered Madhavapeddi Shreedhar and George Varghese paper &amp;ldquo;Efficient fair queuing using deficit round-robin&amp;rdquo; [1]. While the session was not so much about the relatively simple algorithmic details of deficit-round-robin (still worth checking out) we talked about:
  Its benefits over basic FIFO queuing and thus its impact for congestion controlled traffic (tcp) compared to not congestion controlled traffic (udp).
  Its wide deployment still seen today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>24th DistSys Reading Group - BBR Congestion-Based Congestion Control</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-04-06-24th-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-04-06-24th-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>After a bit of a break due to current pandemic we decided to carry on and continue our meetings as virtual calls. Ignoring the usual initial hiccups and the missing whiteboard the medium worked well for us.
Topic and reading of this session was the ACM Queue article BBR: Congestion-Based Congestion Control [1], as well as the Dropbox article Evaluating BBRv2 on the Dropbox Edge Network [2].
We started off with a quick recap of the previous session covering why we need congestion control, how one can view a multi-hop connection as a single hop connection with a single bottleneck and most importantly the fact that the Internet is the largest distributed system that most of the time &amp;ldquo;just works&amp;rdquo; due to congestion control.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elimination back-off stack performance</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-04-01-elimination-backoff-stack-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-04-01-elimination-backoff-stack-performance/</guid>
      <description>I recently stumbled upon the idea of an Elimination Back-off Stack promising to be a parallel, linearizable and lock-free stack. In case you are not familiar with it, I would suggest either reading my previous post or the corresponding paper [1] itself. Being quite intrigued by the ideas of the above stack I wrote my own implementation in Rust with a little help from crossbeam.
In this post I will compare my implementation to other stack implementations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elimination back-off stack</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-03-28-elimination-backoff-stack/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-03-28-elimination-backoff-stack/</guid>
      <description>Reading The Art of Multiprocessor Programming [1] I came across the Elimination Back-off Stack [2] datastructure introduced in 2004 by Danny Hendler, Nir Shavit, and Lena Yerushalmi. It promises to be a parallel lock-free stack.
How can a stack allow parallel operations without going through a single serialization point, e.g. a Mutex or an Atomic? Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into it.
A lock-free stack A lock-free stack, also often referred to as a Treiber stack [3] due to Kent Treiber, operates on top of a lock-free linked list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving the Prometheus team</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-03-14-leaving-prometheus-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-03-14-leaving-prometheus-team/</guid>
      <description>In January 2017 I joined the company CoreOS as a test-engineer helping the monitoring team and the rkt container engine team write reliable software. Eventually I joined the CoreOS&amp;rsquo; monitoring team full-time as a software engineer and ultimately was invited to be part of the upstream Prometheus team due to my contributions to the Alertmanager sub-project.
Over the next 2 years and 4 month I worked a lot on Alertmanager, e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23rd Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-02-18-23rd-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-02-18-23rd-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>At the end of the previous session one of us suggested to dive into congestion control algorithms. This has found a greater echo, thus the 23rd session covered congestion control algorithms in general and TCP&amp;rsquo;s Reno as well as TCP&amp;rsquo;s Tahoe in particular.
This weeks reading was:
  Chapter 13 &amp;ldquo;TCP Reno and Congestion Management&amp;rdquo; from the comprehensive online book &amp;ldquo;An Introduction to Computer Networks&amp;rdquo; [1] from the Loyola University Chicago.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22nd Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-28-22nd-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-28-22nd-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>In the 22nd session we took a look at io_uring - a new Kernel interface for asynchronous I/O. Tyler, who is currently implementing an io_uring library in Rust [4] for his database sled [7] guided us through the concepts as well as a bunch of source code.
Tyler started off introducing the status quo of I/O interfaces within the Linux Kernel like read, pread and preadv, jumped over to asynchronous I/O like aio and eventually helped us develop a sense of what the perfect asynchronous I/O interface of the future could look like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21st Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-24-21st-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-24-21st-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>We started the new year with a session on epidemic / gossip protocols. To decide what to read I compiled the following list of papers that I either enjoyed reading in the past, or that were recommended to me. The Swim (Scalable failure detection and membership protocol) paper won the poll.
 Das, Abhinandan, Indranil Gupta, and Ashish Motivala. &amp;ldquo;Swim: Scalable weakly-consistent infection-style process group membership protocol.&amp;rdquo; Proceedings International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20th Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-11-28-20th-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-11-28-20th-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>Last Tuesday we meet again to discuss different attacks and possible countermeasures for distributed hash tables. More in particular we looked at Kademlia and its security extension S/Kademlia [1], possible eclipse attacks on the Ethereum network [2], a novel approach of hiding its own connection buckets as well as using an existing social graph as a network topology in the Whanau paper[3], security extensions to the Chord DHT [4], as well as a larger study of different security techniques for DHTs [5].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19th Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-10-27-19th-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-10-27-19th-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>I have been organizing a distributed systems paper reading group in Berlin for the last year. We meet every other week discussing a paper in the distributed systems space. This could be anything from Chandy–Lamport&amp;rsquo;s algorithm for global distributed snapshots [1] to things like conflict free replicated datatypes [2]. The event is open for anyone interested. I only ask people to come prepared.
In the last meeting (19th) we covered distributed hash tables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metric driven performance optimization</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-06-25-metric-driven-performance-optimization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-06-25-metric-driven-performance-optimization/</guid>
      <description>Within my work at Red Hat and Kubernetes SIG instrumentation  I have been working on kube-state-metrics , a Prometheus  exporter exposing the state of a Kubernetes cluster to a Prometheus monitoring system. In particular I have focused on performance optimizing metric rendering for both latency as well as resource usage. Below I want to describe our approach of metric driven performance tuning, using Prometheus to monitor kube-state-metrics on top of Kubernetes, which in itself enables Prometheus to monitor Kubernetes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Metric Rendering in kube-state-metrics</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/talks/optimizing-metric-rendering-in-kube-state-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/talks/optimizing-metric-rendering-in-kube-state-metrics/</guid>
      <description>Kube-state-metrics exposes Prometheus metrics of the state of a given Kubernetes cluster. The project uses the standard Prometheus client Golang library, which is not optimized for the very specific use case of kube-state-metrics.
This talk covers different optimizations like metric caching and improved text marshaling dividing CPU usage by a factor of 6 and memory and response time by a factor of 3 through introducing an intelligent Prometheus metric cache in the code hot path and optimizing memory allocations during response generation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-Service Monitoring</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/talks/self-service-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/talks/self-service-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>Monitoring plays a crucial role in a microservice architecture. Restricting the management and configuration of the monitoring stack to the operations team results in workflow bottlenecks. Instead one could provide a self-service monitoring platform, enabling each team to easily setup monitoring for their applications and customize it to their needs. This gives each team the ability to deeply introspect their application, benchmark new features and alert on failures on their own.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-healing Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/talks/self-healing-k8s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/talks/self-healing-k8s/</guid>
      <description>What If Component xxx Dies? Introducing Self-Healing Kubernetes
Kubernetes promises healing your application on all kinds of failure scenarios, but why not self-heal Kubernetes itself?
This talk introduces self-hosted Kubernetes (K8s inside itself) to autonomously recover from failure scenarios with the help of e.g. itself, systemd and checkpointing. We will ask and answer questions like “What happens when xxx dies”. The theory will be followed by a demo on a live cluster showcasing what happens when we kill central Kubernetes components, like the API-Server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End-to-end monitoring with the Prometheus Operator</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/talks/end-to-end-monitoring-with-the-prometheus-operator/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/talks/end-to-end-monitoring-with-the-prometheus-operator/</guid>
      <description>Kubernetes is a powerful system to build and operate a modern cloud-native infrastructure. Monitoring with Prometheus ensures that Kubernetes stays healthy. Prometheus is a stateful application, so operating it in a cloud native environment can be a challenging task. The Prometheus Operator makes running highly available Prometheus clusters, and even an entire end to end monitoring pipeline, easily manageable. Max will explain the functionality of the Prometheus Operator and describe a desirable end-to-end monitoring stack, including alerts and dashboards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/talks/introduction-to-k8s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/talks/introduction-to-k8s/</guid>
      <description>Distributing and deploying software inside (Docker-) containers for security, isolation and ease of use is the new big thing. But once you got all your services nicely wrapped - who takes care of all these containers?
The open source project Kubernetes, originating from Google, helps you manage containerized applications, as the operating system of your datacenter, treating hundreds of machines as a single resource pool. This talk introduces the core concepts of Kubernetes, its benefits and its huge ecosystem and gives you an idea of how Google controls parts of their gigantic infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving user and developer experience of the Alertmanager UI</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/talks/improving-user-and-developer-experience-of-the-alertmanager-ui/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/talks/improving-user-and-developer-experience-of-the-alertmanager-ui/</guid>
      <description>Alertmanager deduplicates, groups, and routes alerts from Prometheus to all kinds of paging services. With it comes a dated UI which does not live up to the expectations of the users, nor does it attract new contributors.
From this talk, you will learn how we addressed these issues when building the new UI from scratch. We made it friendlier to users by removing unnecessary domain language noise. In addition we added new power features such as filtering and grouping.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Triathlon</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2017-06-11-triathlon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2017-06-11-triathlon/</guid>
      <description>Finished my very first Triathlon today here in Berlin. I survived the swimming way better than I thougt, biking wasn&amp;rsquo;t a big problem, but the 10 k at the end were more of a stumbling then a running.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angels Island</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2017-02-12-angels-island/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2017-02-12-angels-island/</guid>
      <description>Sunday five mile hike around Angels Island. Great to get out of the city from time to time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick run through SF</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2017-02-11-quick-run-through-sf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2017-02-11-quick-run-through-sf/</guid>
      <description>My first 16 miles run. Nearly blacked out at the end. Amazing route!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back in Germany</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-17-back-in-germany/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-17-back-in-germany/</guid>
      <description>After two delayed flights, one canceled flight and two lost bags I made it back home to Germany.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back in San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-08-back-in-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-08-back-in-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>Made it back to San Francisco. Crashed on a good friends couch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flying to Las Vegas</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-06-flying-to-las-vegas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-06-flying-to-las-vegas/</guid>
      <description>On my way back to San Francisco I made a quick stop in Las Vegas. A friend I met in Austin showed me around. Visited Downtwon, the strip and the Red Rocks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tourist Tour through Austin</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-04-tourist-tour-through-austin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-04-tourist-tour-through-austin/</guid>
      <description>I went to the Texas State Capitol, learned a bunch about Texas history gaining independence, joined a local hiking Meetup and looked at the graffiti park.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First Yoga Class</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-01-first-yoga-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-12-01-first-yoga-class/</guid>
      <description>20:20 - Hi Max, wanna join Yoga Class tonight? 20:21 - Sure, never tried though. 20:30 - Class starts  My first Yoga class. It was extremly exhausting. Definitely doing it again some time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accomodation at Barton Springs Road</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-30-accomodation-at-barton-springs-road/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-30-accomodation-at-barton-springs-road/</guid>
      <description>I got an AirBnB across the Colorado River fairly close to downtown. My hosts are great. Looking forward to the next days. Surrounded by great restaurants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flight to Austin</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-28-flight-to-austin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-28-flight-to-austin/</guid>
      <description>I am going to Austin Texas for the NodeJS Interactive conference. Am looking forward to some great talks both on NodeJS itself and microservice architectures. Flying over night - saving one night of accomodation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pierce Point</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-27-pierce-point/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-27-pierce-point/</guid>
      <description>Hiking to the Pierce Point. We have seen something that looked like a fox and plenty of Elks. It is a scenic view along the coast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting Berkeley</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-26-visiting-berkeley/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-26-visiting-berkeley/</guid>
      <description>With two friends of mine I wen to Berkeley. We started with downtown Berkeley and then made our way up to the university campus. We hiked all the way up to Lawrence Hall of Science from where we had an amazing view over the entire bay.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thanksgiving</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-24-thanksgiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-24-thanksgiving/</guid>
      <description>A very fun friend of mine from Covo with whom I shared a lot of great discussions on coding and code quality in particular invited me over for Thanksgiving. I felt very welcome. We talked a lot about politics. It is super interesting to see an American point of view on it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alcatraz</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-19-alcatraz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-19-alcatraz/</guid>
      <description>I booked a tour for Alcatraz. My first time on a boat in the Bay Area. The weather was horrible - setting the perfect mood for visiting a prison.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friday Evening Friendsgiving</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-18-friday-evening-friendsgiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-18-friday-evening-friendsgiving/</guid>
      <description>A cowoker / great friend of mine from Covo invited me over for a friendsgiving at his place. Like the day before, great food and a great party in a beautiful house in Potrero Hill.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Friendsgiving at Covo</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-17-friendsgiving-at-covo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-17-friendsgiving-at-covo/</guid>
      <description>The coworking space I currently work at, Covo, arranged a friendsgiving for lunch. Everybody contributed to the dinner. We had plenty of food and a great time. My first friendsgiving.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting the Google Campus</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-13-visiting-the-google-campus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-13-visiting-the-google-campus/</guid>
      <description>There was a conference at the Google campus on Sunday. I really enjoyed the talks. I was especially interested in the topics architecture and artificial intelligence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Golden Gate Bridge</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-12-golden-gate-bridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-12-golden-gate-bridge/</guid>
      <description>I woke up reasonably early on Saturday to go to the Golden Gaten Bridge. The bus ride from Ingleside took me an hour. I started my hike in the Presidio park along the west coast. I found some lonely beaches. I felt nothing like being in a city. Afterwards I walked over the Golden Gate Bridge where two friends of mine, Simon and Marc, picked me up. We drove to Muir Beach, Stinson Beach, Tiboron and Sausalito.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding the Perfect Coworking Space</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-02-finding-the-perfect-coworking-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-02-finding-the-perfect-coworking-space/</guid>
      <description>As we are working from San Francisco for the rest of the month, we were looking for a coworking space. Well, &amp;hellip; not just one coworking space, but the coworking space. We started our search on Wednesday with the coworking space, Thursday we looked at NextSpace, Wework and Bespoke In the evening we decided to go with Bespoken until we passed by two more coworking spaces (Covo and Impact Hub) on our way to a restaurant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB Launchpad</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-01-mongodb-launchpad/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-01-mongodb-launchpad/</guid>
      <description>Been to the MongoDB Launchpad event, a release event for their new version. Sadly it was more of a marketing event than a nerd event. But the location was really nice with a view on the Golden Gate Bridge (Fort Mason 2 Marina Blvd San Francisco, CA).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving to San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-01-moving-to-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-11-01-moving-to-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>I moved to San Francisco to the Coliving Club. I will miss Palo Alto.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pub Crawl</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-30-pub-crawl/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-30-pub-crawl/</guid>
      <description>I went out with my roommates again - this time a pub crawl mostly in the city center.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halloween Party or Art Event in San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-29-halloween-party-or-art-event-in-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-29-halloween-party-or-art-event-in-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>We, my roommates and I, went to a crazy Halloween Party atPier 70 in San Francisco, an old industrial complex. The costumes of the other guests were amazing. They seemed to be inspired by the Burning Man festival.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JS Meetup in San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-27-js-meetup-in-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-27-js-meetup-in-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>I have been to a JS meetup in San Francisco in the Yelp HQ. It is an impressiv building from 1925 known as the Pacific Bell Building.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rooftop apartment office</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-25-rooftop-apartment-office/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-25-rooftop-apartment-office/</guid>
      <description>Worked in a rooftop apartment today with a view over entire Palo Alto and parts of the bay area. Sadly I can&amp;rsquo;t work from there every day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacker House One</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-24-hacker-house-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-24-hacker-house-one/</guid>
      <description>My first day at the first Hacker House in Palo Alto. House cleaning is every Tuesday. I arrived on Monday. The people here are amazing. Many startup founders - smart people all over the place. The location, 635 Webster St., Palo Alto, is awesome, right in the center. This makes up for sleeping in a room with six other guys, living in an apartment with 21 guys with two bathrooms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hearst Castle</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-23-hearst-castle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-23-hearst-castle/</guid>
      <description>Hearst Castle is a huge Landmark. We did a tour with an amazing tour guide, it was like Mr. Hearst showed us around himself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Los Angeles and Santa Monica</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-22-los-angeles-and-santa-monica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-22-los-angeles-and-santa-monica/</guid>
      <description>We did a very short walk through Los Angeles and I took a longer walk around Santa Monica and (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venice,_Los_Angeles)[Venice beach]. I liked the last two a lot. In the next two days I am heading back to the San Francisco bay area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>San Diego</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-19-san-diego/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-19-san-diego/</guid>
      <description>We started of at theBalboa Park, walked down to Little Italy, visited the USS Midway aircraft carrier museum ship and walked back to the car through down town. This was my first time on an aircraft carrier, these things are huge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Last Man Standing</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-18-last-man-standing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-18-last-man-standing/</guid>
      <description>Signed up for audience seats at the sitcom Last Man Standing. We had to arrive at 3 for the show to start at 6. They hired a comedian just to cheer up the audience - a little strange. It is very interesting to see how small the entire set actually is. Most of the times the actors only need 2 tries for one scene - extremly professional.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University of California Riverside</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-17-university-of-california-riverside/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-17-university-of-california-riverside/</guid>
      <description>We walked over the campus of the University, ate in the canteen and worked outside at desks with solar powered outlets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palm Springs</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-16-palm-springs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-16-palm-springs/</guid>
      <description>First night in the Los Angeles area mostly for the mexican restaurant El Mirasol Cocina Mexicana across the street. There are many huge beautiful villas like little oasis in Palm Springs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kings Canyon National Park</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-15-kings-canyon-national-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-15-kings-canyon-national-park/</guid>
      <description>We did a 10 Miles hike in the Kings Canyon National Parkup to the Mist Falls. This has been my favourite National Park so far because of the very untouched nature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hana Haus</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-13-hana-haus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-13-hana-haus/</guid>
      <description>During the day we worked in the fancy Hana Haus, a coworking space by SAP. Afterwards we stayed for a Design Thinking Talk at the same place and finished the evening at a steake house close to the Apple offices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker HQ</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-12-docker-hq/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-12-docker-hq/</guid>
      <description>We visited the Docker HQ for a meetup.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pinnacles National Park</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-11-pinnacles-national-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-11-pinnacles-national-park/</guid>
      <description>We did two hikes, including a cave and three scary tarantulas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fleet Week</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-09-fleet-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-09-fleet-week/</guid>
      <description>We went to the San Francisco Fleet Week. My first time to see SF downtown during daylight and the Golden Gate Bridge. Perfect weather in a very crowded town.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Santa Cruz</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-09-santa-cruz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-09-santa-cruz/</guid>
      <description>Exploring the beach area with all the surfers, working in a cafe and the hotel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Computer History Museum</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-07-the-computer-history-museum/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-07-the-computer-history-museum/</guid>
      <description>First thing to do in Silicon Valley- the computer history museum. It is an amazing museum with all the hardware I have ever dreamed of. Showed me how much I don&amp;rsquo;t know about computers, especially anything below logic gates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flying to San Francisco</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-06-flying-to-san-francisco/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2016-10-06-flying-to-san-francisco/</guid>
      <description>Düsseldorf &amp;mdash;-&amp;gt; London &amp;ndash;A380&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; San Francisco</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>