<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>talk on Max Inden</title>
    <link>https://max-inden.de/tags/talk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in talk on Max Inden</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://max-inden.de/tags/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;Connecting everything, everywhere, all at once&#34; @IPFS-Thing</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/2023-04-16-connecting-everything-everywhere-all-at-once/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/2023-04-16-connecting-everything-everywhere-all-at-once/</guid>
      <description>How you can connect everything (browsers &amp;amp; non-browsers), everywhere (public or private), all at once (using libp2p).
Slides</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;DOS Defense - Do’s and Don’ts&#34; @IPFS-Camp</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/2022-11-02-dos-defense-dos-and-donts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/2022-11-02-dos-defense-dos-and-donts/</guid>
      <description>I presented at IPFS Camp 2022 on mitigating Denial-of-Service attacks in peer-to-peer networks. I discussed resource management strategies such as enforcing backpressure and provided examples of coding pitfalls to avoid in Rust and Go. You can find the recording and slides of my talk below.
Slides DOS Denial-of-service attack Hard in peer-to-peer as identities are cheap Relevant for any scarce resource, e.g. CPU, memory(, file descriptors) Do&amp;rsquo;s Bound EVERYTHING Once a bound is exceeded: Drop item (good) Enforce backpressure (good) Do&amp;rsquo;s Backpressure Slow consumer should slow down a fast producer Can improve resource utilization Can improve latency Don&amp;rsquo;ts 1 2 3 4 5 6 // Decode the length prefix of a message.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;Hole punching in the wild&#34; @FOSDEM</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/2023-02-05-hole-punching-in-the-wild/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/2023-02-05-hole-punching-in-the-wild/</guid>
      <description>Dennis and I presented Hole punching in the wild, learnings from running libp2p hole punching in production, measured from vantage points across the globe in the network devroom at FOSDEM 2023.
At FOSDEM 2022 I presented libp2p&amp;rsquo;s hole punching mechanism, overcoming NATs and firewalls with no dependencies on central infrastructure. One year has passed since. We rolled it out to live networks. We launched a large measurement campaign with many volunteers deploying vantage points in their home network, punching holes across the globe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;Peer-to-peer Browser Connectivity&#34; @FOSDEM</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/2023-02-05-peer-to-peer-browser-connectivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/2023-02-05-peer-to-peer-browser-connectivity/</guid>
      <description>I presented an overview on Peer-to-peer Browser Connectivity options in the network devroom at FOSDEM 2023.
Connecting from the browser to a public server with a valid TLS certificate is easy. But what if the server has a self-signed certificate? What if it isn&amp;rsquo;t public? What if it is another browser?
This talk covers the intricacies of browser communication beyond the standard browser-to-server use-case. I will give an overview of the many protocols available and how they can be used in a peer-to-peer fashion without sacrificing authenticity, confidentiality or integrity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;Hole punching with libp2p&#34; @p2p-paris</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/2022-04-30-hole-punching-with-libp2p/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/2022-04-30-hole-punching-with-libp2p/</guid>
      <description>We’ll take a closer look at the recently added decentralized hole punching feature, allowing NAT and firewall traversal without the need for any central coordination servers (STUN and TURN).
Recording</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;Introduction to and State of libp2p&#34; @p2p-paris</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/2022-04-29-introduction-to-and-state-of-libp2p/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/2022-04-29-introduction-to-and-state-of-libp2p/</guid>
      <description>We will discuss the current state of the project, eyeball the various language implementations, take a look at the many live networks running on top of libp2p today and finally cover the project roadmap for the years to come.
Recording</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;Peer-to-peer hole punching without centralized infrastructure&#34; @FOSDEM</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/peer-to-peer-hole-punching-without-centralized-infrastructure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/peer-to-peer-hole-punching-without-centralized-infrastructure/</guid>
      <description>Gave a talk on hole punching in libp2p at FOSDEM 2022.
Peer-to-peer hole punching without centralized infrastructure
How libp2p can traverse NATs and firewalls without coordination through central STUN and TURN servers.
libp2p is a universal, cross-platform, multi-language, modular peer-to-peer networking library powering multiple large-scale networks, for example IPFS.
In the first part of the talk we’ll present the basic building blocks of the library and explain how they fit together.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk &#34;State of libp2p&#34; @FOSDEM</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/state-of-libp2p/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/state-of-libp2p/</guid>
      <description>Gave a talk on the state of libp2p at FOSDEM 2022.
State of libp2p
Status quo and future roadmap of the peer-to-peer networking library libp2p.
libp2p is a universal, cross-platform, multi-language, modular peer-to-peer networking library powering multiple large-scale networks, for example IPFS, Ethereum 2, Filecoin or Polkadot.
We will discuss the current state of the project, eyeball the various language implementations, take a look at the many live networks running on top of libp2p today and finally cover the project roadmap for the years to come.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk Intro to libp2p</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/intro-to-libp2p/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/intro-to-libp2p/</guid>
      <description>On Tuesday 20th of July I gave a talk introducing libp2p, a modular network stack.
Recording Slides </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk Optimizing Metric Rendering in kube-state-metrics</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/optimizing-metric-rendering-in-kube-state-metrics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/optimizing-metric-rendering-in-kube-state-metrics/</guid>
      <description>Kube-state-metrics exposes Prometheus metrics of the state of a given Kubernetes cluster. The project uses the standard Prometheus client Golang library, which is not optimized for the very specific use case of kube-state-metrics.
This talk covers different optimizations like metric caching and improved text marshaling dividing CPU usage by a factor of 6 and memory and response time by a factor of 3 through introducing an intelligent Prometheus metric cache in the code hot path and optimizing memory allocations during response generation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk Self-healing Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/self-healing-k8s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/self-healing-k8s/</guid>
      <description>What If Component xxx Dies? Introducing Self-Healing Kubernetes
Kubernetes promises healing your application on all kinds of failure scenarios, but why not self-heal Kubernetes itself?
This talk introduces self-hosted Kubernetes (K8s inside itself) to autonomously recover from failure scenarios with the help of e.g. itself, systemd and checkpointing. We will ask and answer questions like “What happens when xxx dies”. The theory will be followed by a demo on a live cluster showcasing what happens when we kill central Kubernetes components, like the API-Server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk End-to-end monitoring with the Prometheus Operator</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/end-to-end-monitoring-with-the-prometheus-operator/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/end-to-end-monitoring-with-the-prometheus-operator/</guid>
      <description>Kubernetes is a powerful system to build and operate a modern cloud-native infrastructure. Monitoring with Prometheus ensures that Kubernetes stays healthy. Prometheus is a stateful application, so operating it in a cloud native environment can be a challenging task. The Prometheus Operator makes running highly available Prometheus clusters, and even an entire end to end monitoring pipeline, easily manageable. Max will explain the functionality of the Prometheus Operator and describe a desirable end-to-end monitoring stack, including alerts and dashboards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk Intro to Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/introduction-to-k8s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/introduction-to-k8s/</guid>
      <description>Distributing and deploying software inside (Docker-) containers for security, isolation and ease of use is the new big thing. But once you got all your services nicely wrapped - who takes care of all these containers?
The open source project Kubernetes, originating from Google, helps you manage containerized applications, as the operating system of your datacenter, treating hundreds of machines as a single resource pool. This talk introduces the core concepts of Kubernetes, its benefits and its huge ecosystem and gives you an idea of how Google controls parts of their gigantic infrastructure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk Improving user and developer experience of the Alertmanager UI</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/post/improving-user-and-developer-experience-of-the-alertmanager-ui/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/post/improving-user-and-developer-experience-of-the-alertmanager-ui/</guid>
      <description>Alertmanager deduplicates, groups, and routes alerts from Prometheus to all kinds of paging services. With it comes a dated UI which does not live up to the expectations of the users, nor does it attract new contributors.
From this talk, you will learn how we addressed these issues when building the new UI from scratch. We made it friendlier to users by removing unnecessary domain language noise. In addition we added new power features such as filtering and grouping.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
