<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>paper on mxinden</title>
    <link>https://max-inden.de/tags/paper/</link>
    <description>Recent content in paper on mxinden</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://max-inden.de/tags/paper/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Elimination back-off stack</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-03-28-elimination-backoff-stack/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-03-28-elimination-backoff-stack/</guid>
      <description>Reading The Art of Multiprocessor Programming [1] I came across the Elimination Back-off Stack [2] datastructure introduced in 2004 by Danny Hendler, Nir Shavit, and Lena Yerushalmi. It promises to be a parallel lock-free stack.
How can a stack allow parallel operations without going through a single serialization point, e.g. a Mutex or an Atomic? Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into it.
A lock-free stack A lock-free stack, also often referred to as a Treiber stack [3] due to Kent Treiber, operates on top of a lock-free linked list.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>23rd Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-02-18-23rd-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-02-18-23rd-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>At the end of the previous session one of us suggested to dive into congestion control algorithms. This has found a greater echo, thus the 23rd session covered congestion control algorithms in general and TCP&amp;rsquo;s Reno as well as TCP&amp;rsquo;s Tahoe in particular.
This weeks reading was:
  Chapter 13 &amp;ldquo;TCP Reno and Congestion Management&amp;rdquo; from the comprehensive online book &amp;ldquo;An Introduction to Computer Networks&amp;rdquo; [1] from the Loyola University Chicago.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>22nd Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-28-22nd-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-28-22nd-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>In the 22nd session we took a look at io_uring - a new Kernel interface for asynchronous I/O. Tyler, who is currently implementing an io_uring library in Rust [4] for his database sled [7] guided us through the concepts as well as a bunch of source code.
Tyler started off introducing the status quo of I/O interfaces within the Linux Kernel like read, pread and preadv, jumped over to asynchronous I/O like aio and eventually helped us develop a sense of what the perfect asynchronous I/O interface of the future could look like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21st Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-24-21st-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2020-01-24-21st-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>We started the new year with a session on epidemic / gossip protocols. To decide what to read I compiled the following list of papers that I either enjoyed reading in the past, or that were recommended to me. The Swim (Scalable failure detection and membership protocol) paper won the poll.
 Das, Abhinandan, Indranil Gupta, and Ashish Motivala. &amp;ldquo;Swim: Scalable weakly-consistent infection-style process group membership protocol.&amp;rdquo; Proceedings International Conference on Dependable Systems and Networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20th Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-11-28-20th-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-11-28-20th-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>Last Tuesday we meet again to discuss different attacks and possible countermeasures for distributed hash tables. More in particular we looked at Kademlia and its security extension S/Kademlia [1], possible eclipse attacks on the Ethereum network [2], a novel approach of hiding its own connection buckets as well as using an existing social graph as a network topology in the Whanau paper[3], security extensions to the Chord DHT [4], as well as a larger study of different security techniques for DHTs [5].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>19th Distributed Systems Paper Club</title>
      <link>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-10-27-19th-paper-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://max-inden.de/blog/2019-10-27-19th-paper-club/</guid>
      <description>I have been organizing a distributed systems paper reading group in Berlin for the last year. We meet every other week discussing a paper in the distributed systems space. This could be anything from Chandy–Lamport&amp;rsquo;s algorithm for global distributed snapshots [1] to things like conflict free replicated datatypes [2]. The event is open for anyone interested. I only ask people to come prepared.
In the last meeting (19th) we covered distributed hash tables.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>